Guide to the Taube Archive of the International Military Tribunal (IMT) at Nuremberg, 1945-46 mt839rq8746
Virtual Tribunals
Taube Archive of the International Military Tribunal (IMT) at Nuremberg
1945-46
Virtual Tribunals
International Court of Justice. Library
International Military Tribunal
mt839rq8746
9920 item(s)
Scope and contents
The Taube Archive of the International Military Tribunal (IMT) at Nuremberg, 1945-46 collection includes court transcripts, indictments, sentences, briefings, minutes, etc, related to the proceedings of the International Military Tribunal (IMT) at Nuremberg. The first twenty-eight boxes contain: a) Exhibits submitted to the Tribunal by Prosecution and Defense; b) Official Transcripts as taken by Court Reporters, of Court and Commission proceedings; c) Document Books of Prosecution and Defense; d) Trial Briefs, Opening and Closing Statements of Prosecution; e) Final Pleas and Clemency Pleas of Defense; f) Indictment; g) Judgement, Dissenting Opinion and Sentences; h) Minutes of Tribunal Meetings; i) Rules of the Tribunal, Orders of the Tribunal, Court Rulings on the Final Record; and j) Lists, indices and miscellaneous related material. Material was inventoried box by box. The last nine boxes contain only electronic transcriptions of the proceedings before the International Military Tribunal.
The digital collection contains approximately 250,000 pages of digitized paper documents (transcripts of the hearings in English, French, German and Russian; written pleadings; evidence exhibits filed by the prosecution and the defense; documents of the Committee for the Investigation and Prosecution of Major War Criminals; the judgment).
The official archives of the International Military Tribunal of Nuremberg (the "Nuremberg Trial Archives") were entrusted to the International Court of Justice (ICJ) in 1950. The ICJ and its Registry are the custodians of the entire archive, which includes the original print documents that are available in digital form here, audio recordings of the trial's proceedings, and evidentiary films.
Source: The Registry, International Court of Justice. (2018). Nuremberg Trial Archives, The International Court of Justice: Custodian of the archives of the International Military Tribunal at Nuremberg (2nd ed.) and the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
International Military Tribunal (IMT) Cases
The IMT's single case tried 24 defendants, all charged with being "leaders, organizers [and] instigators [of] and accomplices" in the crimes defined in the Charter. They were chosen to represent a cross-section of Nazi diplomatic, economic, political, and military leadership. Adolf Hitler, Heinrich Himmler, and Joseph Goebbels could not be tried because they committed suicide at the end of the war or soon afterwards. Hermann Göring was the highest ranking Nazi official among the defendants.
In the end, only 21 defendants appeared in court. German industrialist Gustav Krupp was included in the original indictment, but he was elderly and in failing health. The Tribunal decided in preliminary hearings to exclude him from the proceedings. Nazi Party secretary Martin Bormann could not be located. Borman was thus tried in absentia. Head of the German Labor Front Robert Ley committed suicide on the eve of the trial. (United States Holocaust Memorial Museum)
Joining the lead defendant, Reichsmarschall and Successor Designate to Hitler, Hermann Wilhelm Göring, were:
Rudolf Hess, former Deputy to the Führer Joachim von Ribbentrop, Reich Minister for Foreign Affairs Wilhelm Keitel, Chief of the High Command of the German Armed Forces Ernst Kaltenbrunner, Head of the Reich Main Security Office and highest ranking officer of the Nazi party Schutzstaffel (SS) at Nuremberg Alfred Rosenberg, racial theory ideologist and Reich Minister for the Eastern Occupied Territories Hans Frank, Governor General of the Occupied Polish Territories Wilhelm Frick, Reich Minister of the Interior and Reich Protector for Bohemia and Moravia Julius Streicher, Editor-in-Chief of the antisemitic newspaper Der Stürmer Walther Funk, Reich Minister of Economics and President of the German Reichsbank Hjalmar Schacht, former Reich Minister of Economics and President of the German Reichsbank Karl Doenitz, Commander-in-Chief of the German Navy and, briefly, successor to Hitler as Head of the German Government Erich Raeder, former Commander-in-Chief of the German Navy Baldur von Schirach, Head of the Hitler Youth Fritz Sauckel, Plenipotentiary of the Nazi slave-labour programme Alfred Jodl, Chief of the High Command of the German Armed Forces Operations Department Franz von Papen, former Reich Chancellor and Vice Chancellor Arthur Seyss-Inquart, Reich Commissar for the Occupied Netherlands Albert Speer, Reich Minister for Armament and Munitions and Hitler's chief architect Konstantin von Neurath, Reich Minister of Foreign Affairs and later Reich Protector for Bohemia and Moravia Hans Fritzsche, Ministerialdirektor of the Reich Ministry of Propaganda International Military Tribunal (IMT) Crimes
(a) Crimes against peace: namely, planning, preparation, initiation or waging of a war of aggression, or a war in violation of international treaties, agreements or assurances, or participation in a common plan or conspiracy for the accomplishment of any of the foregoing
(b) War crimes: namely, violations of the laws or customs of war. Such violations shall include, but not be limited to, murder, ill-treatment or deportation to slave labour or for any other purpose of civilian population of or in occupied territory, murder or ill-treatment of prisoners of war or persons on the seas, killing of hostages, plunder of public or private property, wanton destruction of cities, towns or villages, or devastation not justified by military necessity
(c) Crimes against humanity: namely, murder, extermination, enslavement, deportation, and other inhumane acts committed against any civilian population, before or during the war, or persecutions on political, racial or religious grounds in execution of or in connection with any crime within the jurisdiction of the Tribunal, whether or not in violation of the domestic law of the country where perpetrated.
The first of these charges, (a), was subdivided in the indictment, which thus contained four counts, of which the defendants each faced his own permutation.
Count one (common plan or conspiracy) was prosecuted by the United States, and count two (crimes against peace) by the United Kingdom. Count three (war crimes) and count four (crimes against humanity) were prosecuted jointly by France and the Soviet Union, according to whether the crimes in question had been committed in Western or Eastern Europe.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in the Nuremberg Trial Archives are made available for online viewing courtesy of the International Court of Justice for non-commercial, personal, research and/or study/educational purposes.
All requests for usage beyond online viewing of the Nuremberg Trial Archives should be directed to the Library of the Court, library@icj-cij.org
Zeppelinfeld (Nuremberg, Germany); Nuremberg War Crime Trials, Nuremberg, Germany, 1946-1949; International criminal courts; Trials (Crimes against humanity); Criminal procedure (International law); Crimes against humanity; International Court of Justice. Library; International Military Tribunal
- Audio recordings of proceedings, 4361 item(s)
  Scope and Contents
  Contemporaneous audio recordings of the complete trial proceedings at the IMT Nuremberg, from reading of the indictments, to opening statements, the presentation and cross-examination of evidence at trial, closing statements and final judgments.
  - November 1945, 187 item(s)
    - November 20, 1945, 27 item(s)
      - Lord Justice Lawrence opening session reading of Indictment. Part 1, 1945-11-20 from 10:00 - 10:10; H-5260_0001A_1; 1 item(s) 0:12:07 16" aluminum Presto instantaneous discs (Box Electrical transcription boxes)
  - December 1945, 325 item(s)
    - December 1, 1945, 14 item(s)
      - Tribunal's decision on Hess. Questioning by British prosecutor and German counsels, 1945-12-01 from 10:00 - 10:14; H-5260_0181A_1; 1 item(s) 0:14:03 16" aluminum Presto instantaneous discs (Box Electrical transcription boxes)
        Arrangement
        Note from the ICJ Registry: For this track, the information on the disc label and found in the gramophone disc inventory (the "Index to Electrical Transcriptions of International Military Tribunal", H-5192) does not appear to be accurate. The information provided here is based on a review of the audio.
- Document books, 392 item(s)
  Compendia of exhibits presented at trial, compiled for judicial review, organized according to defendant.
  - Hermann GOERING - No. 1, H-0668; 1 item(s) 100 pages Folders (Box 6)
    PRELIMINARY NOTES TO DOCUMENTS BOOKS AND TRIAL BRIEFS: For purpose of this inventory, Document Books have been identified merely by the name and number of the Document Book. No attempt has been made to catalog the documents contained therein.
    English language
- Empty folder, 148 item(s)
  These are digitized images of file folders that were archived originally as a part of the collection, but where the original contents may have been removed or relocated elsewhere before the digitization.
  - Folders, 148 item(s)
    - RF Exhibit 1401, H-4891; 1 item(s) 6 pages Folders (Box 24)
      General
      Note: Folder contains only two certificates, and photostat statement that RF 1401 is the same document as RF 1323
- Evidentiary exhibits, 3462 item(s)
  These records contain documentary and physical evidence that was submitted at trial by the parties to the proceedings as exhibits for judicial review.
  - US exhibits, 958 item(s)
    - Package photostats, 54 item(s)
      - USA Exhibit 388, H-2953; 1 item(s) 91 pages Package photostats (Box 17)
        Foto-Mappe Nr. 44
        German language
    - Film in box, 3 item(s)
      - USA Exhibit 167 "Nazi Plan" Reels 19-20, H-5243; 1 item(s) 00:17:21 Film in box (Box 27)
        Nazi Plan
  - USSR exhibits, 67 item(s)
    - Envelopes, 35 item(s)
      - USSR Exhibits Nos. 1-6, H-1473; 1 item(s) 189 pages Envelopes (Box 13)
        PRELIMINARY NOTES TO EXHIBITS: In the following Box, exhibit numbers with a dash between are inclusive. For example, "Nos l-6" indicates Nos: l, 2, 3, 4, 5 & 6. Whereas "Nos 1, 6" indicates only the two numbers specified, namely No 1 and No 6.
        Russian language
- Final pleas and clemency pleas, 111 item(s)
  These records contain legal pleadings and supporting documentation from defense counsel for the accused, seeking review of judgments and clemency in sentencing.
  - Folders, 111 item(s)
    - Final Plea: Alfred ROSENBERG, H-1302; 1 item(s) 164 pages Folders (Box 11)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO FINAL PLEAS: The Final Pleas listed below have various titles on the cover pages, such as Final Plea: Closing Arguments, Final Pleading, Final Pleadings, Plea, Pleadings, Plaidoyer, the Case of.
      pp. 3-86 plus cover page
      French language
- Indictments, 1 item(s)
  Official charging documents, authored by the prosecution, to indict those accused of crimes under the IMT Nuremberg Charter.
  - Envelopes, 1 item(s)
    - Indictment against Hermann GOERING et al., lodged with the International Military Tribunal, 6 October 1945, 1945-10-06; H-2752; 1 item(s) 45 pages Envelopes (Box 16)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO PROSECUTION CLOSING SPEECHES: The Prosecution Closing Speeches in English have various titles on the cover page, such as: Final Argument, Closing Statement, Final Statement, Final Speech.
      printed
- Judgments, dissenting opinions, and sentences, 11 item(s)
  These records contain the final verdicts of the judges at the IMT Nuremberg, including dissenting opinions and sentences rendered against those found guilty of crimes charged.
  - Folders, 11 item(s)
    - Original signed Judgment of the IMT, 1 Oct 1946, 1946-10-01; H-2754; 1 item(s) 108 pages Folders (Box 16)
      pp. 178-283 (typewritten)
- Lists, indices, and miscellaneous, 67 item(s)
  These materials include compilations and summaries of trial testimony and other evidence presented pertaining to the charges in the trial and the verdicts rendered against the accused.
  - Folders, 62 item(s)
    - SD Affidavits, (a) Letter of Defense Counsel Dr. Gawlik,2 August 1946, requesting translation of SD Affidavits, (b) List of SD Affidavits, (c) Affidavits 1-20, 1946-08-02; H-1408; 1 item(s) 67 pages Folders (Box 12)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO AFFIDAVITS: The affidavits in this box presumably relate to the defense of the accused organizations. For classification as to which were exhibits, etc., detailed scrutiny of the affidavits together with related portions of the record will of course be required. The majority of these affidavits are signed originals.
      (a) (German), (b) List, 15 pages (German), (c) (German and English)
      German language; English language
- Minutes of tribunal meetings, 1 item(s)
  Compendium of minutes recorded contemporaneously of meetings (9 Oct 1945 - 1 Oct 1946) where the judges of the IMT Nuremberg convened to discuss and decide administrative and procedural matters.
  - Folders, 1 item(s)
    - Minutes of International Military Tribunal Meetings, 9 Oct 1945 - 1 Oct 1946, Nos. 1-100, 1945-10-09 to 1946-10-01; H-2786; 1 item(s) 219 pages Folders (Box 16)
- Official commission transcripts, 234 item(s)
  These are the official transcripts of the Commissions appointed by the IMT for the hearing of witnesses or the presentation of affidavits relating to the accused organizations. Recorded contemporaneously by professional clerks.
  - Folders, 234 item(s)
    - Official Commission Transcript, Robert BRILL, 21 May 1946, 1946-05-21; H-0908; 1 item(s) 55 pages Folders (Box 8)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO OFFICIAL TRANSCRIPT OF THE COMMISSIONS: Box 8 contains the Official Transcript of the Commissions appointed by the IMT for the hearing of witnesses or the presentation of Affidavits relating to the accused organizations. The inventory below indicates either the name of the witness or the accused organization.
      (a) Typescript - pp. 1-29 (English), (b) Mimeograph - pp. 82-106 (German)
      English language; German language
- Official court transcripts, 723 item(s)
  These records are contemporaneous transcription of live courtroom proceedings at the IMT Nuremberg, recorded by professional clerks of the tribunal and archived with the records of trial.
  - Volumes, 38 item(s)
    - Vol. 38: Official Court Transcript, 27-31 August 1946, 1946-08-27 to 1946-08-31; H-1216; 1 item(s) 679 pages Volumes (Box 10)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO RUSSIAN TRANSCRIPTS: The Russian Transcripts are bound in 39 volumes containing the authentic Russian text either typewritten or mimeographed. In each volume are found one or more unnumbered pages: the table of contents (sometimes pasted on outside of cover, sometimes inserted in volume in loose form), Russian certificates and sometimes English certificates.
      pp. 19202-19876
- Rules, rulings, and orders, 10 item(s)
  Rules of procedure and evidence promulgated by the IMT Nuremberg to govern the proceedings of trial.
  - Envelopes, 3 item(s)
    - Incomplete copies of International Military Tribunal Orders, H-5169; 1 item(s) 219 pages Envelopes (Box 26)
      5 pages (English), 212 pages (German)
  - Folders, 7 item(s)
    - International Military Tribunal Orders, H-5170; 1 item(s) 54 pages Folders (Box 26)
      52 pages
- Statements and speeches, 56 item(s)
  These are the text of the opening and closing statements delivered by prosecuting attorneys at the trial.
  - Envelopes, 1 item(s)
    - Introduction to French Closing Speech on responsibility of Defendants, by Mr. Champetier de Ribes, H-5161; 1 item(s) 13 pages Envelopes (Box 26)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO PROSECUTION CLOSING SPEECHES: The Prosecution Closing Speeches in English have various titles on the cover page, such as: "Closing Address", "Final Speech", "Final Address", "Final statement".
      pp. 1-10 plus cover page
- Trial briefs, 37 item(s)
  These trial briefs are official court filings authored by the U.S. and British prosecution teams making legal arguments about particular defendants, incidents, and theories of liability.
  - Folders, 37 item(s)
    - U.S. Trial Brief LL against the Defendant Wilhelm FRICK, H-1240; 1 item(s) 51 pages Folders (Box 11)
      PRELIMINARY NOTES TO DOCUMENTS BOOKS AND TRIAL BRIEFS: For purpose of this inventory, Document Books and Trial briefs have been identified merely by the name and letter. No attempt has been made to catalog the documents contained therein or to count the pages.